Don Tobin Cartoons
Don Tobin Cartoons
1944-1965
1953-1965
Tobin, Don.
10 linear ft.
The Don Tobin Cartoons collection contains over 2,300 original cartoons from the comic strip The Little Woman (1953-1965), hundreds of original magazine cartoons (1946-1957), some sketches (circa 1945-1955) and one item of promotional material from The Little Woman (1964).
2653507
Biographical History
Donovan Tobin (b. 1916), commonly known as Don Tobin, was an American cartoonist and animator.
Don Tobin was born in Austin, Texas and attended the University of California, graduating in 1936.
Tobin was an animator in the early 1940s and worked on such features as Disney's Bambi, Dumbo, Pinocchio and the "Rite of Spring" segment in Fantasia. In 1941 he also helped animate the following shorts: Donald Duck's "Golden Eggs," Mickey Mouse's "The Nifty Nineties" and "Pluto's Playmate." He also worked on "Donald's Snow Fight," "Pluto Junior" and Goofy's "Olympic Champ" released the following year. Tobin left Disney after the 1941 strike, moving to magazine cartoons. For a time, he was part of a clan of cartoonists working at Laguna Beach that included John Dempsey, the Interlandi brothers, Ed Nofziger and Virgil Partch.
He drew gag cartoons for several publications including, Collier's magazine, the Ladies' Home Journal and the Saturday Evening Post. Tobin created the comic strip The Little Woman in 1953. The Little Woman was about a housewife named Emily Butterworth, who was reminiscent of his mother-in-law. A book of the comic strip was published in 1965.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Don Tobin Cartoons is split into the following series: Clipping, Notebooks, Original artwork and Promotional material.
The Clipping (undated) series contains one magazine clipping featuring one of Tobin's cartoons from the Saturday Evening Post.
The Notebooks (undated) series consists of eight notebooks featuring original gags and captain ideas.
Original artwork (1945-1965) is the bulk of the collection. This series includes original cartoons published in Collier's, the Saturday Evening Post and other original cartoons from various magazine publications. These original cartoons from other magazine publications were often unlabeled, though some appear to have been published in the Ladies' Home Journal. Sketches for magazine cartoons are also part of this series. Although, original art from the comic strip The Little Woman makes up the bulk of this series. Also important to note are rough comic book sketches and an original self portrait.
Promotional material (1964) includes one promotional booklet of The Little Woman from King Features Syndicate.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized by series and arranged by item type. Materials from the same comic strip or series are at times not housed together because of their varying specific dimensions.
Related Material
Original artwork from Disney's the "Father, Dear Father" segment of The Nifty Nineties short, is located in the
Father, Dear Father Collection
.
has collections of more than 150 cartoonists. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Cartoonists; Tobin, Don.; King Features Syndicate.; Little woman (comic strip).; Saturday evening post.; American wit and humor, Pictorial.; Caricatures and cartoons -- United States.; Cartoonists -- United States.; Women household employees -- Caricatures and cartoons.; Cartoons (humorous images); Cartoons (working drawings); Comic strips.; Promotional materials.; Cartoonists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Don Tobin, 1969.
Inventory
- Clipping
  - Saturday Evening Post cartoon, undated; crayon drawing on reverse side; 1 item (Box 1)
- Notebooks
  - Gag and cartoon caption ideas, undated; 8 items (Box 1)
- Original artwork
  - Comic strip
    - The Little Woman
      Click here for a detailed inventory of original The Little Woman cartoons.
      - Daily cartoons, 1953; 1957; 191 items (Oversize 1)
      - Daily cartoons, 1958 Dec-1959 Sep; 210 items (Box  2)
      - Daily cartoons, 1959 Oct-Dec; 1960; 270 items (Box  3)
      - Daily cartoons, 1961; 274 items (Box  4)
      - Daily cartoons, 1962; 293 items (Box  5)
      - Daily cartoons, 1963; 295 items (Box  6)
      - Daily cartoons, 1964; 293 items (Box  7)
      - Daily cartoons, 1965; 249 items (Box  8)
      - Sunday cartoons, 1961 (Oversize 7)
      - Sunday cartoons, 1962 Jan-Jun (Oversize 7)
      - Sunday cartoons, 1962 Jul-Dec (Oversize 8)
      - Sunday cartoons, 1963 (Oversize 8)
      - Sunday cartoons, 1964-1965; 98 items (Oversize 6)
  - Comic strip sketches, undated; drawings on front and back; 15 items (Oversize 9)
  - Magazine cartoons
    - Collier's
      Cartoons published in Collier's magazine and organized by captian or series title. Some items are painted in full color.
      - A Bib for Daddy, 1953; 7 items (Oversize 2)
      - A - D, circa 1949-1953; 7 items (Oversize 2)
      - First Man on the Moon Returns, 1952; 8 items (Oversize 2)
      - G - H, circa 1949-1953; 7 items (Oversize 2)
      - I - J, circa 1949-1953; 29 items (Oversize 3)
      - L - N, circa 1949-1953; 8 items (Oversize 3)
      - O - P, circa 1949-1953; 9 items (Oversize 3)
      - S - T, circa 1949-1953; 10 items (Oversize 3)
      - Summer Sonata, 1952; 8 items (Oversize 3)
      - Tardy Wife, 1952; 8 items (Oversize 3)
      - Uncaptioned, circa 1949-1953; 1 item (Oversize 3)
      - W - Y, circa 1949-1953; 14 items (Oversize 3)
    - Magazine publications
      Original cartoons published in various magazines, including Ladies' Home Journal.
      - January - February, 1944; 1948-1949,; 1951,; 1955; 5 items (Oversize 2)
      - March, 1946-1947; 1954,; 1957; 4 items (Oversize 2)
      - April, 1950-1951; 2 items (Oversize 2)
      - May - June, 1947; 1955; 2 items (Oversize 2)
      - July, 1948; 1951,; 1956; 4 items (Oversize 2)
      - August, 1949-1950; 1953,; 1957; 1 item (Oversize 2)
      - September, 1950; 4 items (Oversize 2)
      - October, 1946; 1948,; 1951; 3 items (Oversize 2)
      - November, 1947; 1949-1951,; 1956; 4 items (Oversize 2)
      - December, 1946-1947; 1951; 4 items (Oversize 2)
      - Miscellaneous published cartoons, undated; 36 items (Oversize 2)
    - Saturday Evening Post
      Original cartoons published in the Saturday Evening Post; organized by caption. Some cartoons have drawings on the reverse side of the items.
      - A - B, circa 1945-1955; 9 items (Oversize 4)
      - C - D, circa 1945-1955; 15 items (Oversize  4)
      - F - G, circa 1945-1955; 14 items (Oversize 4)
      - H, circa 1945-1955; 20 items (Oversize 4)
      - I, circa 1945-1955; 46 items (Oversize 4)
      - J, circa 1945-1955; 8 items (Oversize 4)
      - K - L, circa 1945-1955; 4 items (Oversize 4)
      - M, circa 1945-1955; 11 items (Oversize 5)
      - N, circa 1945-1955; 13 items (Oversize 5)
      - O - P, circa 1945-1955; 14 items (Oversize 5)
      - S - T, circa 1945-1955; 14 items (Oversize 5)
      - Uncaptioned, circa 1945-1955; 10 items (Oversize 5)
      - U - W, circa 1945-1955; 28 items (Oversize 5)
      - Y, circa 1945-1955; 8 items (Oversize 5)
  - Self portrait, 1948; 1 item (Box 1)
  - Sketches
    Majority of sketches have crayon drawings on the reverse side.
    - A - E, circa 1945-1955; 23 items (Box 1)
    - F - H, circa 1945-1955; 15 items (Box 1)
    - I - J, circa 1945-1955; 65 items (Box 1)
    - L - N, circa 1945-1955; 14 items (Box 1)
    - O - P, circa 1945-1955; 10 items (Box 1)
    - S - T, circa 1945-1955; 20 items (Box 1)
    - Uncaptioned, circa 1945-1955; 2 items (Box 1)
    - W, circa 1945-1955; 24 items (Box 1)
    - Y, circa 1945-1955; 14 items (Box 1)
- Promotional material
  - The Little Woman, 1964; 1 item (Box 1)
    King Features Syndicate booklet